Council on Foreign Relations Digital Sound Recordings, 1953-1989: Finding Aid MC104.13
Public Policy Papers
Council on Foreign Relations Digital Sound Recordings
1953-1989
Public Policy Papers
Council on foreign relations
Princeton University. Library. Special Collections
MC104.13
24 boxes
The Council on Foreign Relations is a nonprofit, nonpartisan research and national membership organization dedicated to promoting improved understanding of international affairs and to contributing ideas to United States foreign policy. These digital sound recordings have been transfered from original reel to reel tapes of Council meetings as part of an ongoing project. The meetings feature a range of speakers on topics relating to foreign policy, including mainly government officials and businessmen from the United States and abroad.
General
This material forms part of the Council on Foreign Relations Records, call number MC104, held at the Seeley G. Mudd Manuscript Library. See other "Other Finding Aid Section for more information.
Scope and Contents
The digital sound recordings of the Council on Foreign Relations were transfered from original reel to reel tapes of Council meetings. Transcripts of meetings were created until 1963; from 1964 through 1970, there is no record of what was said at any events mounted by the Meetings Department at the Council unless the event was "on the record" and the speaker issued written text. The Council's records contain a small number of tapes from the early 1970s. The only record of the intellectual content of the Meetings Program after 1964 is these surviving tape recordings of the opening presentations of speakers, and occassionally a question and answer section. In 1978, the Council began to tape selected meetings for use by members who were unable to attend important meetings. At the end of each fiscal year, the Council president, Director of Meetings, and Director of Programs would assist the Director of Special Programs is selecting a portion of the year's taped meetings to be sent to the archives. Usually those selected were heads of state, foreign ministers, United States Cabinet members and other distinguished visitors. No programs held at the Washington, D.C. office of the Council were ever recorded.
Until the transfer was completed in April 2006, the meeting audio was inaccessible to researchers due to preservation concerns about tape handling and playing.
Portions of the recordings may have poor audio quality; the recordings often begin and end abruptly, and rarely feature the question and answer section of the meeting.
Conditions Governing Access
All Council on Foreign Relations records are closed for 25 years after the date of their creation.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The Council on Foreign Relations Sound Recordings are available to researchers in mp3 format. Users must have access to some form of mp3 player, such as Quicktime, Windows Media Player, or Winamp. Preservation master copies were made in WAV format, but are not available online.
Other Finding Aids
The Council on Foreign Relations Digital Sound Recordings form part of the The Council on Foreign Relations Records (collection MC104). A Finding Aid for the entire collection is available online: Council on Foreign Relations Records Finding Aid.
The records of the Council on Foreign Relations Meetings Department are described in a finding aid, which includes a list of speakers at meetings held from 1924-1992: Council on Foreign Relations Meetings Records Finding Aid.
The Studies Department Records of the Council on Foreign Relations are described in a separate finding aid: Council on Foreign Relations Studies Department Finding Aid.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was deposited at the Library in 1998. Title and custody of the collection were formally transferred to Princeton in 2002. Small transfers of more recent records occur annually.
Appraisal
Since 1921, the Council has archived materials relating to its organization, study groups, meetings, and special events. The Council Library and Archives staff reviews records to discard administrative material not conforming to its general retention policy. Items deemed private or inappropriate for transfer are retained by the Council. Based on a memos dated 10 September 1984, 15 October 1984, and 19 December 1986 from Council records, Council administration routinely "purged" their collection of general meeting tapes, selecting only a few to go to the Council library and archives department.
Accruals
The Mudd Manuscript Library does not anticipate receiving any further sound recordings from the Council on Foreign Relations, but will continue to digitize and make available its holdings of Council audio recordings as resources permit.
Existence and Location of Originals
The original reel-to-reel tapes containing the Council's programs are held at the Mudd Manuscript Library as part of the Council on Foreign Relations Records, Series 13: Sound Recordings, 1953-1989.
Existence and Location of Copies
The Mudd Manuscript Library also maintains WAV format preservation master copies of each file.
Related Materials
The Council on Foreign Relations Records Series 4: Meetings, may hold paper records relating to these recordings. In addition, please see the Council on Foreign Relations's website located at http://www.cfr.org for online audio recordings of more recent on-the-record meetings.
Researchers interested in the Council on Foreign Relations may also wish to consult the interview transcripts from Columbia University's Council on Foreign Relations Visual Oral History Project.
Biographical / Historical
The Council on Foreign Relations (the Council) is a nonprofit, nonpartisan research and national membership organization dedicated to promoting improved understanding of international affairs and to contributing ideas to United States foreign policy. The Council has had a large impact in the development of twentieth century United States foreign policy. Its membership has historically been drawn from those in business, government and academia recognized as the nation's opinion leaders in international relations; membership is by invitation only. The Council's basic constituency is its members, but it also reaches out to a wider audience through its publications, Committees on Foreign Relations, Corporate Program, and media efforts, so as to contribute to the national dialogue on foreign policy.
The Studies Department spearheads the Council on Foreign Relation's efforts to promote informed discussion on issues shaping the international agenda and defines the Council's function as a foreign policy research organization. This "think tank" has played a vital role in the Council since its incorporation in the 1920s. The department includes a large number of scholars and research associates who engage each other, Council members, and non-affiliated individuals in research on topics and regions related to United States foreign policy, which historically have included topics such as international trade, arms control, and economic development, and regions such as the former Soviet Union, the Middle East, and Latin America, to name a few. The Studies program produces articles, books, policy reports and papers to disseminate the research undertaken by staff and members.
For a fuller history on the Council on Foreign Relations, see the finding aid for the Council on Foreign Relations Records located at http://arks.princeton.edu/ark:/88435/gb19f5814, Peter Grose's Continuing the Inquiry: The Council on Foreign Relations from 1921-1996, located at http://www.cfr.org/about/history/cfr/ and Michael Wala's The Council on Foreign Relations and American Foreign Policy in the Early Cold War (Providence: Berghahn Books, 1994).
Bibliography
Information in the Organizational History section was gathered from material within the Council's records (notably historical information from the Administration Series and Annual Reports from the Publications Series), as well as the Council on Foreign Relations' website, www.cfr.org. Of special interest are the annual reports, located at http://www.cfr.org/about/annual_report/ and Peter Grouse's Continuing the Inquiry: The Council on Foreign Relations from 1921-1996, located at http://www.cfr.org/about/history/cfr/.
International relations--20th century.; World politics--20th century.; United States--Foreign Relations--20th century.; Born digital.; Proceedings.; Sound recordings.; Council on foreign relations
- Series 1: Digital Sound Recordings, 1953-1989; 24 boxes
  Conditions Governing Access
  All Council on Foreign Relations records are closed for 25 years after the date of their creation.
  Arrangement
  No arrangement action taken or arrangement information not recorded at the time of processing.
  - France's Responsibilities in the World, 1953 March 31; Dillon, Clarence, 1882-1979; Mayer, René, 1895-1972; 1 box (Box 728)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    MC104-1A
    Born digital.
  - The Commonwealth and World Affairs, 1953 April 6; Mansergh, Nicholas.; McKittrick, Thomas H.; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-1B
  - The Present Situation and Future of Kenya Colony, 1954 December 30; Vasey, E. A.; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-2A
    Scope and Contents
    Audio cut off abruptly.
  - Speech on Germany, 1953 April 15; Adenauer, Konrad, 1876-1967.; McCloy, John J. (John Jay), 1895-1989; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-2B
    Speech in German. Audio ends abruptly.
  - European Economic Cooperation: Its Present Situation, 1953 April 20; Marjolin, Robert; Williams, John H. (John Henry), 1887-1980; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-3A
  - Italian Political and Economic Problems and Prospects, 1953 April 28; Bunker, Ellsworth, 1894-1984; Taylor, Myron Charles, 1874-1959; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-3B
  - Problems of United States Policy in the Middle East, 1953 April 30; Altschul, Frank, 1887-1981; Byroade, Henry A. (Henry Alfred), 1913-; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-4A
  - The Present Position of Inter-American Relations, 1953 May 11; Berle, Adolf A., jr., 1895-1971; Oreamuno, J. Rafael; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-4B
  - The Defense of the Eastern Mediterranean, 1953 May 21; Armstrong, Hamilton Fish, 1893-1973; Markezinis, Spyros; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-5A
    Verbatim reading of text of Markezini's speech by unnamed narrator.
    Biographical / Historical
    Hamilton Fish Armstrong was born, the youngest of seven children, April 7, 1893, in a house on West 10th Street. His parents, D. Maitland Armstrong (1836-1918) and Helen Neilson (1845-1927) named him for his great uncle, who was Grant's Secretary of State. His father was an artist, working especially with stained glass, and a one-time Consul General to Italy. Armstrong grew up in New York City and received his education at Gilman Country School in Baltimore, Maryland, and at Princeton University from which he received the A.B. in 1916.
    Following his graduation Armstrong worked in the business department at The New Republic before entering the army in 1917. Commissioned a second lieutenant in October 1917, Armstrong advanced to first lieutenant and became Military Attache to the Serbian War Mission to the United States in December 1917. In November 1918, he received orders to Belgrade to become Assistant Military Attache to Serbia where in January 1919 he became Acting Military Attache.
    Upon his military discharge in June 1919, Armstrong returned to New York to work on the editorial staff of the New York Evening Post, becoming the paper's special correspondent to Eastern Europe in 1921. His time in Serbia kindled in him a lifelong interest in foreign affairs, and in 1921 he became involved with the newly-formed Council on Foreign Relations, created to ensure that the United States' growing role in world affairs be informed and responsible. In 1922 Armstrong accepted a position as managing editor of the Council's magazine, Foreign Affairs, at the request of editor Archibald Cary Coolidge. Upon Coolidge's death in 1928, Armstrong became editor, a position he held until his retirement in 1972. Armstrong also served as the first Executive Director of the Council (1922-1928) and as a Council director from 1928 until 1972.
    As editor, Armstrong travelled frequently, visiting with policymakers including King Alexander of Yugoslavia, Raymond Poincaré, Adolf Hitler, Benito Mussolini, and Neville Chamberlain. He was also well acquainted with many prominent Americans, such as Woodrow Wilson, Franklin D. Roosevelt, and Henry A. Kissinger. He belonged to many important committees and foundations: member of the President's Advisory Committee on Political Refugees; three times delegate to the International Studies Conference (1929, 1933, 1935); trustee and twice president of the Woodrow Wilson Foundation; trustee and once president of the New York Society Library; and trustee of the New York International House.
    Armstrong held many prominent positions during the Second World War. From 1942-44, he served on the United States State Department's Advisory Committee on Post-War Foreign Policies, which produced the original plans for the United Nations. In 1944, he became the special assistant to the United States ambassador in London with the personal rank of minister, before serving in 1944 and 1945 as special adviser to Secretary of State Edward R. Stettinius, working on the charter for the United Nations. At the San Francisco Conference in 1945, he was one of three senior advisers to the United States delegation.
    Armstrong wrote prolifically, penning numerous magazine articles–forty-nine for Foreign Affairs alone–and thirteen books (he edited five others). His books include The New Balkans (1926), Where the East Begins (1929), Hitler's Reich: The First Phase (1933), Europe Between Wars? (1934), Can We Be Neutral? (1936) with Allen W. Dulles, "We or They:" Two Worlds in Conflict (1937), When There Is No Peace (1939), Can America Stay Neutral? (1939) with Allen W. Dulles, Chronology of Failure (1940), The Calculated Risk (1947), Tito and Goliath (1951), Those Days (1963), and Peace and Counterpeace: From Wilson to Hitler (1971). He edited The Book of New York Verse (1918), Foreign Affairs Bibliography (1933) with William L. Langer, The Foreign Policy of the Powers (1935), The Foreign Affairs Reader (1947), and The Foreign Affairs Fifty-Year Reader (1972).
    His activities received much recognition, both at home and abroad. His time in Serbia earned him the Order of the Serbian Red Cross (1918), the Order of St. Sava Fifth Class (1918), and the Chevalier of Order of the White Eagle with Swords (1919). He was awarded the Order of the Crown (Rumania) in 1924 and the Order of the White Lion of Czechoslovakia in 1937. In that year he was made an officer of the Legion of Honor of France and became a commander in 1947. He was appointed a Commander of the British Empire in 1972. He received honorary degrees from Brown (1942), Yale (1957), the University of Basel (1960), Princeton (1961), Columbia (1963), and Harvard (1963).
    Armstrong married three times. Helen MacGregor Byrne became his wife in 1918, and they had one daughter, Helen MacGregor (later Mrs. Edwin Gamble) on September 3, 1923. Armstrong and Byrne divorced in 1938. Armstrong married Carman Barnes in 1945, a marriage which ended in a 1951 divorce. In that same year Armstrong married Christa von Tippelskirch. Armstrong retired from Foreign Affairs in 1972, the fiftieth year of its publication, and died after a long illness on April 24, 1973, at the age of 80.
  - American Opportunities in India and Southeast Asia, 1953 May 27; Bowles, Chester, 1901-1986.; Talbot, Phillips.; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-5B
    First few seconds of the meeting are missing.
  - Ideological Warfare and United States Policy, 1953 June 5; Dulles, Allen, 1893-1969; Kirk, Grayson L.; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-6
    Allen W. Dulles (1893-1969), though a diplomat and lawyer, was renowned for his role in shaping United States intelligence operations, including the longest service as director of the Central Intelligence Agency.
    Born in Watertown, New York, and a Princeton University graduate (BA, Class of 1914; MA 1916), Dulles was the nephew of Robert Lansing, Woodrow Wilson's Secretary of State, and attended the peace negotiations to end the First World War as a member of the American Commission. During his stint in the diplomatic corps, he served in Vienna (1916), Berne (1917), Berlin (1919) and Constantinople (1920) before becoming Division Chief for Near Eastern Affairs (1922). While serving in Washington, D.C., Dulles studied law at night at George Washington University. In 1925, he served as an American delegate to the International Conference on Arms Traffic in Geneva. After earning his LL.D in 1926, Dulles joined the Wall Street law firm of Sullivan and Cromwell, where his brother John Foster was a managing partner. But Dulles did not practice law so much as utilize his knowledge of government processes and officials to assist the firm's corporate clients conduct business. (In fact, Dulles would not pass the bar until 1928.) However, diplomacy would always be Dulles's primary interest and in 1927, he spent six months in Geneva as legal adviser to the Naval Armament Conference.
    In New York, Dulles joined the Council on Foreign Relations, eventually was named a director and enjoyed the friendship of fellow Princetonian Hamilton Fish Armstrong '16, the editor of the Council's journal, Foreign Affairs. Together they authored two books ( Can We Be Neutral? (1936) and Can America Stay Neutral? (1939)). He also continued to serve the United States government in diplomatic capacities, including representing the United States at a League of Nations arms conference in 1932-1933.
    During the Second World War, Dulles took a step that changed his life and ultimately American history. He joined the Office of Strategic Services (OSS), the intelligence service, serving as chief of the Bern, Switzerland office. From there he established himself as a highly successful intelligence gatherer and operator, penetrating the German Foreign Ministry Office as well as the "July 1944" anti-Hitler conspirators. He also played a role in the events that led to the surrender of the German Army in northern Italy.
    In 1948, Dulles's reputation led to his being named chairman of an intelligence review committee that faulted the organization of the then fledgling Central Intelligence Agency. In 1950, he was named Deputy Director of Plans of the CIA, the covert operations arm of the agency; in 1951 he became the number two person in the organization. After Eisenhower's election in Nov 1952, Dulles was appointed to the CIA's directorship. His brother, John Foster Dulles, served as Eisenhower's Secretary of State, and the two men would work closely during their joint service.
    The CIA under Dulles's leadership established the dual policy of collecting intelligence through a wide variety of means, as well as taking direct action against perceived threats. In the former category fell such notable achievements as the U-2 spy plane program, the cooptation of Soviet Lieutenant General Pyotr Popov, and the tapping of a sensitive East Berlin phone junction by tunneling under the Berlin Wall.
    The CIA's efforts in the area of direct action during Dulles tenure were notable for both their successes and failures. CIA operatives orchestrated the overthrow of the government of Iran in 1953 and Jacob Arbenz's regime in Guatemala in 1954. However, efforts to oust Castro from Cuba following his rise to power consisted of a serious of failures culminating in the disastrous Bay of Pigs invasion in April 1961. Though John F. Kennedy had asked Dulles to remain at CIA, after the invasion and the political fallout, Dulles, already past retirement age, resigned.
    In retirement, Allen Dulles wrote books (including two autobiographical works) about his career in intelligence and appeared on numerous television programs to discuss foreign policy. He was called to public service once again, in 1963, when he was named to the Warren Commission. His connection to the CIA and its activities in Cuba would fuel later speculation about possible government complicity in Kennedy's assassination.
    Dulles married Martha Clover Todd (known as Clover) of Baltimore, Maryland in 1920. She died in 1974. They had three children, Clover Todd (known as Toddy), Joan, and Allen Macy. Dulles's son sustained a near-fatal head wound while serving with the Marines in Korea, relegating him to supervised care for life.
  - Problems of German Rearmament, 1953 July 1; Blank, Theodor; Heusinger, Adolf; McCloy, John J. (John Jay), 1895-1989; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-7A
  - The Effects of American Policy on Britain's Economic Position, 1953 August 24; Gaitskell, Hugh, 1906-1963; Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell), 1891-1986; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-7B
  - The Korean Settlement, 1953 September 17; Robertson, Walter S.; Rusk, Dean, 1909-1994; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-8A
  - Indian Neutrallism, 1953 September 21; Chanda, Anil K.; Johnson, Joseph E. (Joseph Esrey), 1906-1990; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-8B
  - The Duty and Responsibility of France in the Problems of the Day, 1953 September 29; Pinay, Antoine; Wriston, Henry M. (Henry Merritt), 1889-1978; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-9A
  - Trends and Developments in Africa, 1953 October 7; Armstrong, Hamilton Fish, 1893-1973; Gunther, John; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-9B
  - The Basis of an Egyptian-British Settlement, 1953 October 13; Hussein, Ahmed; Johnson, Joseph E. (Joseph Esrey), 1906-1990; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-10A
    After the introduction there are 8 minutes of blank tape.
  - The Future of the British Labour Party, 1953 October 22; McKittrick, Thomas H.; Younger, Kenneth, 1908-1976; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-10B
  - Voices of America, Dinner in Honor of Delegates to the New York Conference of Leaders of Institutes of World Affairs, 1953 October 27; Altschul, Frank, 1887-1981; Wriston, Henry M. (Henry Merritt), 1889-1978; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-11A
  - Problems of Yugoslavia's Relations with the West, 1953 November 4; Gross, Ernest A.; Mates, Leo; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-11B
  - The Implementation of Foreign Policy, 1953 November 9; Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell), 1891-1986; Stassen, Harold E.; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-12A
  - Soviet Economic and Technical Developments, 1953 November 16; Amory, Robert, Jr., 1915-1989; Rockefeller, David, 1915-2017; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-12B
  - German Economic Problems and Future Policy, 1953 November 18; Buttenwieser, Benjamin J.; Handler, Meyer S.; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-13A
  - Problems of Communism in the Caribbean Area, 1953 November 23; Braden, Spruille, 1894-1978; Urrutia, Francisco José, 1872-; 1 box (Box 728)
    MC104-13B
  - Observations on United States Foreign Policy, 1953 December 2; Byrnes, James F.; Davis, John W. (John William), 1873-1955; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-14A
  - Problems of Italy's Relations with the Western Allies, 1953 December 3; Bunker, Ellsworth, 1894-1984; Guidotti, Gastone, 1901-1982; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-14B
  - The Changing Foreign and Domestic Policies of the Soviet Union, 1953 December 7; Robinson, Jeroyd T.; Salisbury, Harrison E. (Harrison Evans), 1908-1993; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-15A
    14 seconds of dead air before program begins. Recording ends after 15 minutes with overdubbed announcement that remainder of speech not recorded because "the loudspeaker system failed."
  - The Far-Eastern Policy of the United States, 1953 December 30; Rockefeller III, John D.; Smith, H. Alexander (Howard Alexander), 1880-1966; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-15B
    12-13 seconds dead air before program begins.